I don't know you've probably come across
this little diagram in the book and it's
quite a complicated diagram so I'm going
to just walk you through it a bit and
then I'll tell you the Egyptian story so
this is this is a sequence of
interconnected causal loops so the
question might be well how does morality
emerge from the bottom and I would say
well especially the morality that's
associated with assuming that attention
is something that's sacred roughly
speaking okay so imagine you see someone
really engaged in something you might
think oh I'd really like to be engaged
like that which is what you would think
right because everyone wants that it's
like I'd like to be engaged okay so then
you might think well this person looks
like they're fully alive something like
that they're not being obsessed by
catastrophes and all that they're into
what they're doing what's that like okay
say well that's associated with creative
exploration and then you might say well
what why is creative exploration useful
and the answer to that is because it can
generate adaptive behavior of all sorts
okay so then what well then you can
imitate the adaptive behavior because we
can use our bodies as representational
devices so we act out the person who's
interested in something so that's
actually in large part why people like
to buy art you know so lots of people
I've seen buy art they like to buy art
because they also have some contact with
the artist and they want to have some
contact with the artist because it's
kind of cool to have contact with an
artist it brings something into their
life and the artist is definitely
someone who's outside standard
hierarchies that's sort of what defines
an artist so then once you imitate the
adaptive behavior then you can play
around with the imitations a bit and you
can ritualize them and then you can
dramatize them and a drama is an
interesting thing once it gets
once it gets formalized you know because
basically what you're doing imagine
little kids that get together they lay
out some rules for pretend play then
they run a sprint and play a simulation
then imagine like little Shakespeare
junior is off to the side and he's taken
some notes and maybe he watches six or
seven different pretend play episodes
and he thinks well this was the most
interesting part of that and this was
the most interesting part of that this
was the most interesting
part of that I think I'll put those all
together make them coherent we'll have a
really good story and what the story is
is an articulated representation of a
dramatic representation of a set of
procedures it's two orders of
abstraction right and you know this
because when you read a book I mean this
doesn't happen to me anymore because I
think I've read too many books but I can
remember when I was a kid when I was
reading a book of fiction it was as if
the the the what was being described was
playing out in my imagination as
embodied figures so you know sometimes
you go to a movie of a book you've read
and you think oh that person doesn't
look anything like the person in the
book you know because you have a
representation of what the person is
like I found as I've got older that and
I don't really understand this is I
don't have that anymore but I still
understand the books so I must have
become so otama ties that that's all
gone it's it's a loss I would say but
anyway it doesn't matter you see that
once you get the bloody drama written
down or even when you can say it when
you can tell a story you're so close to
having the the pattern revealed in an
articulated manner you can't say what
the pattern is but you can describe it
well once you can describe it well
you're right next to philosophy right as
soon as we have a set of dramas that we
can all agree on especially once they
get written down then we can start
thinking about the dramas and that's
when philosophy enters the stage as far
as I can tell it's like the groundwork
for philosophy is already laid by
centuries and centuries of human
interaction and we keep abstracting that
up to the point where we can represent
it and then we can pull out general
principles and we discuss them and
debate about them but that's the birth
of philosophy and all those levels
interplay like it's not just the causal
direction isn't just from creative
exploration forward it's each time you
add a new level that interacts with the
previous level right so you can talk
about how you're going to play or you
can analyze literature you know or you
can think about what you're going to
write about so so each time you add
another level of the capacity for
abstraction you make the whole system
much more dynamic and complex so the
causal links that's why there's all
those
arrows on the outside all of those areas
are interacting with each other so yes
yeah too many arrows yeah let me show
you something here this is quite cool
see that did I show you that before oh
this is so cool it's mind-boggling this
thing okay so the horizontal line you
see all the little squiggles that are
underneath that okay every one of those
lines is a biblical verse and that
length of the line corresponds to how
many references there is to that verse
in other places in the book so you look
at the bloody thing man that thing's
hyperlinked like mad and that's partly
why the book the you know think about
this book like a normal book really what
you do know you go see a movie and
there's a timeline there's a beginning
and a middle and an end
but it's a losery right because the
person who was writing the movie saw the
whole thing at once and so they could
use their knowledge of the ending to
fiddle around with the beginning and
they could use their knowledge of the
middle to fiddle around with the end
that doesn't happen in real life so you
can lay this out now imagine you've got
a story and it's like 5,000 years old
and 150,000 people have edited it and
they all knew the end and the middle and
the beginning and they just go like this
well this means this and that refers to
this and that refers to this and that
refers to this and this means that and
well you end up with that it's like it's
infinitely dense you can't get to the
bottom of it
there's no way and really it's
hyperlinked so you I could you could say
that in a sense the Bible is the world's
first fully hyperlinked document weird
so yep
yes and and part of that's part of
that's actually conscious like one of
the things that people do when they're
criticizing Christianity is say well if
you look at the gospel stories for
example they'll be a little story about
Christ and then there'll be this line
that says thus fulfilling Isaiah's
prophecy and the biblical scholars say
look that was put in later and the
reason it was put in later was because
the the hypothesis of the Savior is
nested in the Old Testament and it keeps
partially coming true with all these
prophets so a prophet is like a partial
Savior and in the Old Testament prophets
are just popping up like mad and usually
what happens is Israel gets degenerate
for one reason or another it's because
the king isn't being a good Marduk
basically and so then a prophet who's
very insightful like Nietzsche or
Dostoyevsky pops up and says hey you
don't pay attention to the orphans and
the widows and you better get your art
together because otherwise God's gonna
come along and like flood you out or
your enemies are gonna stream in and of
course often weirdly enough the Kings
listen because they think god this
person is either completely insane or or
God's talking ding because otherwise he
wouldn't be marching into the court when
I could have his head cut off with one
tenths of a seconds or ders so often
they kind of half pay attention but what
happens and this is Dora a Fry's
interpretation fundamentally is that the
whole Testament is the construction of
an empire Israel it's collapsed because
of its failure to follow the fundamental
moral order then it rises again
collapses rises again collapses the
first story like that is the flood right
and that's a really really old story you
know that the Bible doesn't get quasi
historic until Abraham the stories
before that so that would be like the
creation of the world Adam and Eve the
Tower of Babel Cain and Abel don't know
that's later Noah and then then the
Abrahamic stories start and that's more
like the history of Israel even though
it's also mythologized but the first set
of stories man those things are old who
knows how old really old 50 thousand
years old maybe they're old
so anyways what happens across time is
that people have all these biblical
books and it's like what the
Mesopotamians had to do in order to
organize their society it's like oh
we've got all these writings they're all
sacred hypothetically they contradict
each other
they don't seem to be in any order like
what are we going to do about that and
so then there's this collaboration of
minds across centuries to think oh well
it kind of looks like this might go
there and then this might go there and
this refers to that and this refers to
that and so it is that's Thai it's
trying to it's the collective
imagination of humanity trying to make a
coherent story out of experience that's
what it is and you know it's you might
say well it's our best guess is it true
depends what you mean by true right
that's a very very tricky question
partly this the question it's trying to
answer is how should you act that's not
the story that's not a scientific story
but it's a bloody important question
okay good so Egypt I felt like you know
the story of who discovered buoyancy he
ran through the streets Eureka
who was it Archimedes okay so our
comedians was trying to figure out how
to measure the volume of something and
he I think he wanted to figure out how
you'd determined whether an alloy was
pure gold or not so you'd have to get
the volume of the damn thing and then
maybe add a clump of metal there's no
way you could measure then he figured
out that if you had a tub full of water
and you drop the thing in it the amount
of water that spilled over the edges
would tell you exactly how big the thing
was and then you could weigh your thing
your metal and you could tell what
proportion of it was gold and so he was
so thrilled about that he theoretically
he discovered that when he was in a
bathtub he got it in the water spilled
over
he ran naked through the streets of
whatever town he was in yelling Eureka
Eureka I've got it so so that's an
insight right so I felt like that when i
when i read this egyptian story and i
thought i figured it out so because i
thought wow that's mind boggling so
here's the story so we got to show you
some of these characters
Noorie so the guy in the middle that's
Osiris he's on this pillar so he sort of
represents what pillars represent which
is what hold things up okay and then the
guy on the Left that's Horus and Horus
is he's got the head of a Falken okay
and the reason for that is that Falcons
fly around so they're not attached to
the ground and they can really really
really really see like their birds of
prey and they're about the only animal
who can see better than us so like
Raptors birds of prey they can see like
mad think an eagle that eagle was
standing on the top of the Empire State
Building it could see a dime on the
sidewalk so it's like gold eagle and
then the one on the right is Isis and
Isis is queen of the underworld okay and
then there's one other character here
you see that's a madonna and child
basically there are that character that
Seth and Seth is he's a bad guy now no
one knows what the hell Seth is you know
nobody's been able to figure out what
kind of weird animal that is so who
knows but those are the four main
characters okay so now you've got to
know how they interact here so you got
Osiris and the store there's variants of
this story many but I'm telling you like
one sort of canonical variant so mmm
story of Osiris and Isis and Horus yeah
yeah so and this is the story upon which
Egyptian civilization was based although
it was a very old civilization right
lasted for thousands of years so
Cleopatra there's less time from
Cleopatra to now than there is between
Cleopatra and the pyramids so that kind
of tells the whole old Egypt was it's
like old major civilization lasted a
long time had a powerful story a
powerfully organizing story right way
older than like then the history of
judeo-christian civilization say 2,000
years older than Chinese history it's
old China goes back a long ways though
so you know maybe it's not older than
China but it's something anyway
Oh Cyrus so Osiris was their God who
established Egypt okay so he's like
George Washington if you had George
Washington 2,000 years from now then
George Washington would be Osiris
because he'd be mythologized
right so basically Osiris represents all
the good things that the Egyptians did
to establish order from chaos and set up
the society so Osiris he's a great he
was a great hero when he was young and
he did all sorts of heroic things and he
established the state of Egypt and he
rules over it but he's kind of old and
you can't see as well as he used to and
he's little on the muddle-headed side
but worse than that so he's archaic and
anachronistic and so what that indicates
is that well just like the Americans are
experiencing with their Constitution
it's like hmm things a little on the old
side what should we do with it well we
should update it's like well we don't
want to update it in a way that makes
all chaos break forth you know so
anyways things get archaic just because
they exist right so if you set up a
system of rules it's it's supposed to
adapt to this environment but the
environment keeps wiggling around right
so you have to chase it with the rules
and you have to update the rules as the
landscape changes and that's the
biologists call that the Red Queen
problem roughly speaking which is a
reference to Ellis in Wonderland so
Ellis goes down the rabbit hole and she
finds the Red Queen that's the queen of
chaos mother nature and what and she's
always chopping people's heads off for
arbitrary reasons like yeah and one of
the things she tells alice's here in my
kingdom you have to run as fast as you
can just to stay in the same place and
that's the chronic human problem it's
the problem of entropy right is that you
build something static but things aren't
static so even if it's a useful thing
you've built first of all you got to
maintain the hell out of it because it's
just gonna fall apart but worse than
that the environments running away from
it and so your computers have Osiris
problems all the time it's like they're
just lovely for the first three years
that you own them and then they're
bricks and it's because the underlying
landscape is so dynamic that the
structure loses its validity
you could almost watch it lose its
validity right as a consequence of the
ex
financial increase in computer
intelligence so Osiris great guy when he
was young little old fashioned and worse
he's willfully blind now the Egyptians
insisted on that and that's so cool it's
actually you can be held responsible in
an English common law cart court for
willful blindness and what willful
blindness is the fail is the failure to
realize something you could have
realized so for example if you're a CEO
and you have a crooked chief financial
officer and you think maybe he's crooked
but you decide well I'm not going to
look at the books because then I'd know
and then his malfeasance is brought to
light and you say well I didn't know the
prosecutor will say yeah but you could
have and you knew you could have and you
didn't and so you're culpable for your
own ignorance that's such a brilliant
idea the Egyptians figured this out
Osiris is not only old and you know
decrepit and a little on the alzheimerís
side but he won't pay attention to
things he's had it with that he's
willfully blind and that's a problem
because he has a brother who was the
evil brother of the rightful king which
is a theme that you're all familiar with
have you watched your Disney movies he's
like scar in the Lion King right same
guy or in Aladdin
there's a some bad character I don't
remember his name lurk hmm that's the
guy yeah yeah so you know he's the he's
the evil or Darth Vader in Star Wars
it's like it's he's an archetypal figure
he's the evil brother of the rightful
king now why does the rightful king have
an evil brother that's easy it's because
organizations tend towards decay and
corruption across time that's what they
do the Socialists are really on this
with regards to corporations right they
evil corporations it's like and the and
the right-wingers think oh no it's evil
government so they're just projecting
the archetype of the negative farther
onto the respective organizations when
in fact it's actually a characteristic
of organizations they don't keep an eye
on the damn things they degenerate and
they become corrupt so that's just what
happens you better stay awake to deal
with that so
anyways Osiris has this evil brother
named Seth and Seth the name Seth
becomes Satan through the Coptic
Christians much much much much later so
he's like the precursor to the to the
devil roughly speaking now
Osiris think Seth is alright like like
Skaar does or like Mufasa does with
scart underestimates his danger
something you should never do and so one
day Osiris is just not paying much
attention and Seth gets a big scimitar
something like that chops him into
pieces and then because you can't really
kill Osiris because he's a god as well
as being the founder of the state and
the ruler the only thing you can do is
make it difficult for him to get his act
back together so what Seth does is he
takes Osiris as pieces and he scatters
them all over Egypt and the idea there
is that when corruption overtakes an
organization then things fall apart but
the things aren't actually dead you know
it's like when it corporation falls
apart all the people in it don't die
they just fragment into maybe smaller
groups some companies get spun off or
maybe they fragment all the way down to
the individual level but there's still
potency left in it and the structure is
still there inside each of the
individuals in the sub organization so
you can you can get the damn thing to
fall apart but you can't get rid of it
so fight he does that he scatters these
pieces everywhere so it makes it hard
for Osiris to you know recollection or
to get his act back together so things
fall apart and it's hard for you to get
your out back together that's the idea
and so and then he rules the kingdom
which doesn't work out very well just
like Skaar and The Lion King right
because he's an evil tyrant and all
things considered evil tyranny doesn't
work that well even for the evil tyrant
although you should never assume that an
evil tyrant wants things to work well
not even for him so anyways fine Osiris
has a wife Isis now Isis she's a major
league player in ancient mythology Isis
is queen of the underworld and it's a
real toss-up if you look at our case
cultures whether the top god is the guy
or the order guy like Osiris or the top
god is Isis who's Queen in the
underworld it's like it's 50/50 for sure
and while Isis represents chaos and
Osiris represents order and they should
be in ballots like you know if they're
in harmonious balance like app su and
Tiamat then they produce all sorts of
productive things and if one overwhelms
the other well then it's not so good so
they should be a harmonious couple okay
but now our cyrus is dead
wack he's chopped up and spread
everywhere so op Isis comes out of the
underworld well that's what happened
when the Americans invaded Iraq it's
like well Osiris is gone yeah but what
about Isis oh we forgot about Isis up
she comes chaos
it's like there it is so and is it
better not obviously so you never want
to forget about Isis
so anyways Isis she's not that happy
that Osiris is gone because that's her
husband right and she thinks well that's
not so so helpful so what she does is
she runs around Egypt trying to find his
fellows and the reason for that is
because it it's the seminal apparatus
right it's the seed of the new thing so
what she does is she finds his phallus
and she makes herself pregnant with it
and so bang she goes back down to the
underworld but now she's impregnated so
what does that mean it means when
remarkable things fall apart into chaos
the seeds of something new are
potentially planted okay so fine she
gives birth to Horus like Arthur he's
outside his rightful kingdom just like
Simba it's a standard routine just like
Harry Potter right he's outside his
kingdom and the reason for that is
you're all outside your kingdom it's
like the kingdom is sort of old and
archaic and doesn't quite fit the
circumstances now and it's not all that
fair to you and it's sort of arbitrary
and so you grow up to some degree an
underworld in opposition to it so it's
just an archetypal story so this this
character she finally gives birth to
this character and that's Osiris and
Osiris he's he's quite the character
he's that so sorry that's all sorry his
name is Horace and that
Taurus there and she's the benevolent
goddess of all new things as well as
being the terrible goddess of the
underworld and she knows she's bringing
up Horus and Horus where is he here
there he is
so Horus is this is Falken because he
can fly around and see everything and
he's also the eye of the Egyptians and
so it's like he's like mardik he's eyes
he can see okay so then Horus grows up
and he's thinking hah
not finder world stuff I'd like to have
my kingdom back my rightful Kingdom now
he's different than Osiris and the
reason he's different is because he can
see and normally can he see he will see
and that's a whole different thing so
Horus is not willfully blind and that's
a drag because he can see what's
happened to the kingdom and he can see
Seth and that's not so good it's like
you're in in romeo Dallaire z' position
then aren't you you have to shake hands
with the devil and you know what
happened to romeo Dallaire when that
happened it's like post-trip
you know he was there in Rwanda when
everybody got massacred and the UN
didn't step in property had to watch all
that it was like post-traumatic stress
disorder instantly so it's like if your
eyes open and you can see evil it's like
you better look out because if you're
face to face with real malevolence the
probability that that will damage your
brain is very high you know and one of
the things that's very interesting if
you think about post-traumatic stress
disorder is that often in soldiers it's
it's it's a consequence of something
they did not something they saw so
they'll go out in the battlefield and
they'll find out they're far more
barbarous and cruel and destructive than
they ever possibly imagined and then
they how are they going to fit that into
like corn-fed farm boy from Iowa scheme
you know they can't do it
poof the whole structure is gone it's
very stressful to find that sort of
thing out and the people I've had in my
practice who have had PTSD it's almost
always because they were subjected to
some kind of malevolence like it was
they they came face-to-face with
something evil and in one case for
example I had a client whose boyfriend
was going to
raper she was naive beyond belief and
what what gave her post-traumatic stress
disorder wasn't what he did because she
could fight him off she happened to be
bigger than he was it was the look of
malevolence on his face when he attacked
her that was enough and it she had
severe psychosomatic syndrome symptoms
for four years after that she couldn't
even sleep her whole body would vibrate
and it took a lot of untangling before
we figured out that it was the look on
his face and I've seen that happen other
times it's like becoming face to face
with this sort of thing is no joke so
Horace can see but luckily he's a long
ways from it yep yes I could imagine hmm
yeah that's right that's an at a that's
to put the chaos back in a net one thing
you might want to know about Hitler is
that one day in World War one he'd be
got a medal for bravery in World War one
by the way so Hitler was all sitting
around with his buddies in a trench and
he went off to relieve himself and when
he came back they were all dead because
a shell had landed right in the middle
and so that gave him the idea that he
was saved for something special and I
can tell you if that happened to you you
would feel because we're using your
options
it's a horrible chaotic nasty place
where brutal things happen at random
that's one option or you were saved
because something special is waiting for
you so like to toss up which of those
two you're gonna pick but you're gonna
pick one of them so anyways okay so
Horace he can see set too bad for him so
he goes back to the kingdom and he has
like vicious fight with set and sets
like they're pretty evenly matched and
so the idea there is that even if you're
Oris like son of the of order and and
son of chaos and your eyes are open it's
like it's a
evil it's a pretty even battle so
they're fighting away and Seth gets the
upper hand and he tears out one of
Horace's eyes and then Horace which is
pretty damaging you know that's a drag
to lose an eye so his vision is damaged
by his encounter with evil but Horace
keeps fighting and eventually he
prevails and he gets the eye back and he
banishes Seth to the nether regions of
the kingdom it's like in the Lion King
where you know everything the light
touches is the kingdom and then there's
the nether regions that's where you send
a little Seth so you can't be rid of
them can't kill him he's permanent
because society's will always tend
towards corruption the best you can do
is get the damn guy under control for a
while okay so now Horace has his eye and
you think end of story
pretty good story you could animate that
he just slapped the old eye back in his
head you know pick up the sceptre and
he'd rule happily ever after that isn't
what happens what happens instead is he
pinkie keeps his eye and he goes back to
the underworld and he finds Osiris as
ghost down there and it's sort of
sitting there like this you know it's
because it's all chopped up innit you
know it's a weird combination because on
in one plane it's it's a chopped-up body
that's distributed everywhere but down
in the underworld it's like a ghost a
spirit but it's not very animated it's
sort of in the land of the dead like
Pinocchio's farther in the whale so what
is this whole Horace do well he he gives
Osiris his eye so now blind tradition
can see and then he takes his father
Osiris back up to the surface sort of
now they're a unit arm-in-arm so to
speak and it's the commits the
combination of Horace and Osiris that
rule Egypt and that's what the Egyptians
figured out it's like god that's so
smart it's like well you need this you
need the traditions of the state right
because you need them there if they're
they're vital they hold back chaos you
can't just let that go because then
income seth and up comes the underworld
it's like that's not good you need that
as a bulwark but then it's old and kind
of blind and it's gonna tend towards
corruption and fall over of its own
Kord so how do you solve that and the
answer is you pay attention and you
provide dead tradition with living sight
and if you do that then you get to be
the ruler of the state the rightful
ruler of the state
now the Egyptians basically hypothesized
this took a long time that the Pharaoh
also had an immortal soul he was the
only person who did but the immortal
soul was basically the combination of
Horace and Osiris so the Egyptians
conceptualized that is something that
was eternal so and it was the it was the
eternal it was the central eternal
feature of sovereignty it's so smart and
so as long as the Pharaoh was a good
Horace and Osiris at the same time then
he was the rightful sovereign and he was
reflecting something of the utmost value
and it was immortal it's so smart so
what happened so interestingly they call
this the democratization of Osiris so to
begin with in the Egyptian state you
could only use the Horus Osiris
symbolism if you were either the Pharaoh
to begin with or at least a high-ranking
aristocrat but what happened as Egypt
progressed so to speak as it developed
across time is that the right to use the
symbolism that that was the Horus Osiris
conjunction drifted down the dominance
hierarchy so at some point all the
aristocrats got to use it never drifted
down to like women or common people or
slaves or anything like that but you
know hypothetically the Jews came out of
Egypt and one of the things the Jews
said that went beyond the Egyptians was
that each person was was capable was in
noble din some sense by their potential
relationship with the highest value that
was gone and when the Christians showed
up but that was universalized
everyone had it even prostitutes and
slaves so it's so cool because what
happens is these societies get the idea
of sovereignty laid out in this
phenomenal heavenly drama
and they identify that with the thing
that's at the top of the hierarchy which
is what they should do
but then what happens across time is
everybody wakes up and thinks oh that's
so interesting it's characteristic of
the Pharaoh its characteristic of what
should be sovereign its characteristic
of what the highest value is but it's
actually characteristic of everybody and
it's it's almost impossible to overstate
how important that is because our whole
conception of the idea of natural rights
is predicated on the idea that there's
something about you as an individual
individual whose value is inviolable so
much that it doesn't even matter what
you do so if I see you brutally murder
20 people and there's 50 eyewitnesses
and we know for sure you did it you
still have to be treated as if your
central essence is of tremendous value
and you have to be given due process the
whole law bow down before that and so
then you think well do people believe
this this sort of Horus
Osiris combination and its relationship
to what's ultimately valuable and the
fact that that's embodied in every
person it's like they certainly act like
they believe it and if if they ever
encounter a violation of that in
practice especially social practice
everybody's jumping up and down and
complaining it's like you're trampling
on my rights
what do you mean where'd those come from
what exactly what are they and are they
real or not and if they're not real well
then I can trample over them all I want
because they're not real but if they and
then we can just have an argument about
what human beings are like but if they
are real and they're reflective of an
underlying principle that's continually
attempting to manifest itself in a sense
from the bottom up you better not break
the rules because you're really going
against the cosmic order so that's the
Egyptian story it's like it's
mind-boggling it's no wonder that story
had enough dynamism to to propel a whole
culture across several thousand years
it's like it's a staggering achievement
yeah that's a really good that's a
really good observation this is one of
the things that I I really that that
something new that I've figured out
about all of this in the last five years
for a long time and I still haven't got
this right it's like okay what is your
reaction when one of those principles is
violated so this is like the terror
management question right well for the
terror management people it's fear but
there's a real problem with that because
conservatives tend to be less neurotic
than liberals and conservatives who have
more of a propensity for right-wing
authoritarianism
are more likely to get upset when rules
are violated but the rules seem to be so
I think it's more or I thought that it
was more no no it's not exactly if your
rules get violated it's not exactly fear
although fears part of it it's the
disintegration of your motivational
States into general preparation for for
readiness so that's more like a
generalized stress response and so
everything goes on so that you're able
to deal with what happens next
it's like Gottman's married couples when
they're the ones that are gonna get
divorced right they're very calm on the
surface but underneath it's like the
underworld all hell is broke loose but
then there's been a twist in that
because there's a bunch of data coming
together from all over the world that
basically goes like this is that
right-wing authoritarianism seems to be
based on purity and purity is disgust
control and there's a deep biological
root root for that like people who are
disgust sensitive and concerned with
purity have better standards of hygiene
and they do tend to live longer but
they're also very much against temper
mentally against any form of sexual
contact it isn't bounded by the social
contract and they don't like foreigners
but that's all a clump it's all the same
thing and then we've found recently we
haven't published this yet we've found
recently that we know
conservatives are more conscientious
than liberals and then we found that
conscientiousness fragments into
industriousness and orderliness which
was great because people have been
wondering for five decades how you plug
that proclivity for right-wing
authoritarianism into the general
personality structure and it's
complicated because if you're a radical
liberal like a radical lefty that those
aren't liberals sorry radical lefty a
communist you could be just it seems
like you could be just as authoritarian
as you would be if you were a fascist so
you know that hasn't been quite sorted
out yet but it's the orderliness that
seems to make people have this
right-wing proclivity and it does look
like what they're trying to do is
control disgust so yes what what the
violation of that order a huge chunk of
it seems to be in this entirely new
negative emotion system that we've only
been untangling for twenty years and
it's not associated with neuroticism
liberals are actually more neurotic than
conservatives you know and you could say
well that's because the Conservatives
are so well protected it's like no no
you can't post-hoc use your theory to
predict the opposite of what you would
have predicted before the data comes in
it's like no conservatives are they
should be more physiologically reactive
and there's some evidence that they are
but it does really seem to be discussed
and so to jump ahead a little bit when
after we'd sorted this out know a lot of
the work that was done on disgust was
done by Jonathan hey he's the guy that
deserves the credit for the disgust
purity linkage it's a big deal and he
was pushing the Study of disgust long
before people were paying any attention
to it so good for him when I was working
on the orderliness disgust relationship
I was also reading this book by Hitler
called Hitler's Table Talk and what it
was was a he would talk at his dinners
and they collected it from 1939 to 1940
- and he would like just spout off on
whatever it was that was on his mind and
he was a very open person so it's very
lateral discussion he was very
interested in art and culture but he was
very very orderly and he was a worshiper
of willpower and orderly people are like
that like anorexics are orderly -
orderly they can't even stand their own
it's discussed that their bodies elicit
and they prize the ability to control
their bodies and that's hyper
orderliness that's I think why it's
associated it's generally considered an
upper-middle-class disease and I think
that's because a lot of people who are
at that strata are hyper conscientious
and that gets passed on to their kids
and sometimes that's just too much
anyways one of the things that really
struck me about Hitler's writings and it
really it really blew me away I'll tell
you was that he has a metaphor all of
his thinking's metaphorical and the
metaphor is the Aryan race is a pure
body pure blood pure uncontaminated and
it's under assault by pathogens and
parasites now as soon as you know that
bang you've got is you've got the
underlying dynamic of of his appeal to
the masses and Germans hey they're
orderly so you know one of the things
people say is that what happened in
Germany constituted the decline of
civilization right back to barbarism
it's like ah maybe not conscientiousness
is associated with productivity quite
highly correlations about point four
roughly the same as the correlation with
IQ so conscientiousness is a
prerequisite for civilization and you
can think well why would you be
discussed sensitive and orderly and the
answer might be well how much of your
grain do you want rats and mice to eat
because they eat lots of it right and
keeping the insects out of the food
store that's really really hard so if
you're going to store things up which is
what you're going to do if you're going
to be civilized you better start to be
concerned with hygiene you know so those
things are going to go together well
Hitler was hyper orderly and hyper
discuss sensitive he washes he bathed
four times a day and he was very very
happy about the ability to stand in the
back of his car his parade car and keep
his arm out like this for eight hours he
thought of that as the triumph of the
will
you know when the will seem to be
associated with this propensity towards
orderliness so another thing that's
really interesting and and I still don't
exactly know what to make of this
because it
has complicated my conceptualizations
because a lot of what I'm going to show
you is based on fear and horror and
horror is more like fear plus disgust
it's something you know the difference
between the Blair Witch Project and the
chick Texas Chainsaw Massacre
they're both horror movies but one is
pure fear and the other is almost pure
discussed so disgust seems to be a huge
element of this and it is a primary
response by orderly people to the
violation of moral norms now here's
something weird there was a paper
published in PLoS ONE about a year ago
and what these people did was they they
did I think a within and a cross-country
survey and this wasn't in developed
countries so the question was how much
infectious disease was there in each of
these geographical locales and the next
question was how right-wing were the
people who occupied those areas at the
individual level so they weren't
interested in what the government was
like and what they found was that the
correlation between the prevalence of
infectious diseases and right-wing
authoritarianism at the individual level
was point six it's like and if you know
anything about statistics when you see
point six you just fall over and
hyperventilate because that never
happens it's an effect size that's it's
bigger than 99% of the effect sizes that
you'd ever encounter in the social
sciences it might be 99.9 percent higher
the infectious disease rate the more
right-wing totalitarian the population
why well why do you think they're
regulating inter personal contact and
sexual behavior why well think about it
you know they're trying to minimize
disease transmission vectors
fundamentally now they're not trying to
do that you know what I mean it's an
adaptation keep yourself out of contact
keep yourself isolated
well I don't know I don't know that you
know because lots of those places there
have been infectious diseases for a very
long period of time so but anyway so
that's all very unsettling information
because it sheds it so what it implies
and this is quite cool it implies that
the best way to control right-wing
authoritarianism is to is to instigate
effective public health policy so if you
all if everyone has a sewer and a toilet
and there's no infectious disease
there aren't any right-wing
authoritarians anymore because they're
not necessary now that might be an
overstatement but but it also might not
be you know it's definitely one of the
prerequisites for the kind of stability
and productivity that's characterized
the West is that all of our cities have
functional sewer systems and everybody
has a toilet
it's like turns out that makes a big
difference especially when you don't
have one what should it should bring it
out you know and I'm a reasonably
orderly person you know if I go into a
place that's chaotic especially if it's
chaotic and and and filthy I have a
really really powerful impulse to Tromp
around until it's fixed you know cuz it
just strikes me as things are
deteriorating in a bad direction around
here you know so and I'm not I wouldn't
say that one of my most outstanding
characteristics is orderliness but it's
it's it's up there I'm a reasonably
conscientious person so yeah it's a
visceral response and the visceral
response is something needs to be done
about this you know and you can see how
that's associated with conscientiousness
so what we've been trying to figure out
what makes conscientious people
motivated because conscientiousness
predicts life success it's like well are
they interested in what they're doing
no it's dutifulness okay so why is that
a motivator we're thinking that what the
conscientious person wants is not to
slide into the disgusting bottom of
things
so imagine the hierarchy okay
top is pure bottom is contaminated why
well I can tell you one reason if you
take a given geographical locale this is
even true for songbirds and you rank
order the denizens of that locale by
their dominance position and then you
let a pathogen in the animals die from
the bottom up right so the bottom of the
dominance herky is where all the
pathogens hang out and so if that's
disgusting and it's morally impure and
you're bad if you're down there which is
really a conservative viewpoint in many
ways it's your fault you're there right
and I'm not gonna be there no matter
what and so I think what the
conscientious person is doing is fleeing
the bottom they're not trying to get to
the top except that that's the farthest
away you can get from the bottom and
that's a purity motivation now we don't
know that yet because we haven't been
able to figure out how to motivate
industrious people in the lab so which
is weird right because conscientiousness
predicts life success you'd think that
you could find a task in the lab that
conscientious people would do better
than non conscientious people we've
tried dozens of things and not being
able to do it so now we're trying to
make people embarrassed and ashamed and
see if we could get them to like donate
more to a charity if we do that based on
the idea that what's motivating the
conscientious person is a flight from
contamination it could easily be so it's
quite mind-boggling like it was a twist
it was a twist I never I never forecast
in my conceptualization of these things
but the underworld you know it's a place
of chaos and fear but the underworld
that's hell it's full of sulfurous odors
you know it's it's it's not only
terrifying it's all so disgusting and
its associated symbolically with
disgusting elements of the body as well
so impurity obviously sexual purity for
example is certainly a hygiene purity
admixture and it's it's it's flight from
contamination and no wonder right I mean
the horse sexually transmitted diseases
it's like a major vector of disease
transmission which
that with the AIDS outbreak you know
without without airplanes there wouldn't
be in any AIDS outbreak
you know jet planes plus promiscuity
it's like bang you know we almost
generated a virus that took down the
whole planet so it's no joke when these
things escape from there from their
little box you know you might say well
why aren't people allowed to have the
sexual life they want well the disease
the relationship between disease
transmission and promiscuity is
exponential that's why so you know you
might think well that's no reason it's
like okay maybe not but I don't know how
many hundreds of millions of people have
died from AIDS but it's lots so you know
we'll do that later we're gonna be doing
a lot of distinguishing of that in fact
that's a primary problem of men
distinguishing Isis so that's the
feminine underworld from evil right
right because the because because there
there's a negative element to both of
them if you haven't differentiated
properly then the woman can carry that
whole load that happened to some degree
with Eve for example in the in the in
the Genesis story it's so interesting
because if you read Genesis we're going
to talk about that later
because the person who looks really bad
in Genesis isn't Eve the person who
looks really bad is Adam no so II the
offers in the Apple and like a dance he
takes it but then God comes along
afterwards he's all self-conscious now
and so is Eve and so God comes along to
have a little walk with Adam like he's
used to doing and Adam is hiding in the
bushes cuz he's naked and he doesn't
want God to see and so God calls them on
it says like hey buddy I can see through
bushes you know come out here where I
can talk to you and the Adam says oh I'm
naked I can't come out and God says how
do you figure that out and Adam being
the heroic creature that he was said you
know that woman you made for me it's her
fault it's like well who's the villain
in that story he's such a weasel that
when he gets called on his disobedience
the first thing he does is blame the
woman it's like yeah yeah well that's an
archetypal story I'll tell you that
you know so the temptations of Eve you
know it's like the rapists who blame the
attractiveness of the woman for the rape
it's like the devil made me do it
you know so anyways it's very difficult
to distinguish one form of negative from
another and partly what we're going to
do when we go through the symbolic
differentiation process is put things in
their proper place so I would say that's
this
look that's the wrong direction sorry I
want to show you this one diagram and
then stop
they're so for me that's the map of the
symbolic sphere okay so what you have in
the very background is the dragon of
chaos that's the absolute unknown as
such so you can think about it is the
chaos from which everything else emerges
so that's the unknown unknowns okay on
top of that there's a feminine layer
that's the great mother
and the great mother has a positive
aspect she's mother of all things and
she has a negative aspect and she's
she's the angry time at the force of
death that pulls all biological
creatures back into her grasp creation
and destruction so on top of that
there's culture and culture protects you
from the great mother
just like with Osiris you Isis stays in
the underworld where she belongs but
culture has a negative element and a
positive element so it's it's
patriarchal it's represented by
masculine figures but it has an element
that offers order and an element that
offers tyranny and there's always a
balance between those two and so if
you're a conservative you think hooray
order and if you're a lefty you think oh
no tyranny and you're both right right
because every organization tends towards
tyranny and supports you at the same
time so it's it's right on top of that
there's the archetypal individual now
it's also represented now in masculine
form for reasons that we'll get into
later but it has a positive and a
negative - and the positive is the
creative Explorer moving out into the
darkness with eyes open and then there's
the counterpart of that which is the
thing you shake hands with when you're
romeo Dallaire and you shake hands with
the devil and that's the individual -
and one of the things I would you can
think about this but one of the things
that I really like about this map is
that I think it's the antidote for
ideology and the reason for that is that
you can map ideologies onto this map but
the ideologies only give you half the
story
so like the left-wing story would be
lovely virginal mother nature being
terrorized by the evil corporations as
civilization advances led by the
adversarial individual but the right
wing story is the heroic individual
bringing order into chaos
to avoid the destructive element of of
the natural world so that's like the
frontier myth that that that settled the
United States right heroic pioneers
moving civilization into the chaotic
unknown you just slam those two together
and then you got the real problem which
is that nature slash the unknown is a
creative source of everything and it
will pull you into pieces if if it has
the opportunity and then culture it's
like you can talk and it's warm you
better be happy with culture but the
probability that it's gonna take you and
crunch you and try to turn you into a
carb it's like yeah that's what it's
gonna do that's what it does and then
there's you well yeah you're a wonderful
interesting you know great creature but
look the hell out so and that's right
that and I think the archetypal stories
do a lovely job of continually bringing
those elements together so yeah well
okay so that's good enough